Today I'd like to talk about... Zool 2
今天我想说一下电脑游戏 Zool2
SuperBart:本期会有我的大量个人评论;-)
for the PC, this is the CD-ROM version and there's a very good reason for that.
这是CD版的，一会你就知道干啥用了
You see, this video isn't really about the game itself, even though it's a pretty decent
因为本期视频不是游戏评测
little platformer developed by Gemlin Graphics from 1994.
当然，这个是Gemlin Graphics于1994年开发的平台跳跃游戏
It's not even about the box contents, including a Zooz postcard, sheet of stickers, depictive
盒子里面的明信片啊，贴纸啊，说明书啊，还有海报啥的，我也不会说
manual or even this splendidly coloured poster.
It's about that CD, which incidentally, isn't really necessary for this game.
我要说的是CD，这对于运行游戏来说，并没那么重要
You see, during the mid '90s, CD-ROM was an important, emerging technology, and so even
在上世纪90年代，CD-ROM作为一个重要的科技产品，方兴未艾
games which could fit on a single High Density disk, were baked into CD format, perhaps with
就连可以放进一张软盘的游戏，都得有CD版的
a new 3D rendered intro, or a selection of music.
也许有个新的3D开头动画，或是一段音乐
but nothing really that warranted the expense of a CD-ROM drive.
但为了这些东西，你真没必要买CD
SuperBart：也许现在出的纪念版CD有什么附加内容，但我还是坚持购买初版CD
But it also meant that the odd warning would appear on disks from certain publishers, warning
但是光盘上也有一些发行商的警告
us to "Not play track 1 of this game CD on ANY audio CD Player".
让我们“不要在任意一台CD播放机上播放CD的第一个音轨”
So, it would seem rude not to really.
看上去，这么做真的很不好诶:-P
For this task, I'll be using a Sanyo MCD-Z10 Boombox.
为了本期主题，我用这台三洋MCD-Z10小型音响
SuperBart:前摇要素一
A fine looking machine which oozes that mid 90s sound appeal, an era when we were moving
品相不错，声音很暖，很适合播放上世纪90年代的音乐
rapidly away from cassette tape and onto that new circular digital medium.
那时我们正在抛弃磁带，转向CD
To demonstrate its versatility, first I'll pop in a tape.
为体现它功能的多样性，我先播放盘磁带
Here I have The Crystal Mountain, by Nightlights (otherwise known as Snowkitten)
这是Nightlights(又称Snowkitten)的The Crystal Mountain专辑
I've been listening to their stuff for years, and I love albums on tape, so this is no exception.
我听这盘磁带很多年了，所以它这次被硬点了
There's a bit of wow and flutter from this system, but I imagine a few new bands and
也许走带有些不正常，但我觉得换了皮带
a bit of grease would clean that right up.
上了点油，应该没啥问题
Anyway onto the CD.
无论如何，该放CD了
SuperBart:前摇要素二
Right, track 1, let's see what all the fuss is really about.
好的，音轨1，看看到底有啥不让放的
SuperBart:前摇要素三
Homer: Oh, this was a popular song in the 90s, and
I really don't understand why you young people like it.
SuperBart:金 曲 放 送
Peter Leigh: Welcome to Rick Roll country
Nostalgia Nerd:欢迎来到Rick Roll的世界;-)
Are they being serious?
难道就这个?
Wait, Ahhh, man, I must have picked up the wrong CD.
等会，我拿错CD了:-P
Yep, there you go I left Rick Astley right next to it.
我拿旁边那张Rick Astley了B-)
Ho ho, easy mistake to make!
不(gu)小(yi)心拿错东西很正常呢
SuperBart: 你拿张偶像练习生的CD也行啊（貌似并没有，他没有全长原创专辑）
Let's try that again.
这回拿对了，咱看看
and there we have it, absolutely nothing.
就是这样，啥也没有
No sound what-so-ever.
就是没声
It's also the only track on the disc, so it seems a strange disc to place that warning
这是光盘仅有的音轨，那光盘上的警告就没道理了
on in the first place.
If there were some audio tracks on here as well - as was common on a lot of CD games
要是这个上面像别的游戏光盘那样，有音轨的话
注：Enhanced CD 就是这样，有音乐区和数据区。上世纪90年代后期流行
很多游戏光盘也是这样，诸如Quake和Half Lige
of the time - then it would have made more sense to play this disc on an audio player.
光盘上面的警告就没白说
Also, I find it a little amusing that the track length is 4:04.
还有一点很有趣，这张光盘时长4:04
So just like a 404 wepage error, the contents of this track are apparently absent.
有点像404网页错误，音轨里没有任何信息
But, it might be that we just need to try a different CD player to get a true idea of
不过，也许换个CD播放器就能搞明白里面有啥了
what's going on here.
ok, so now I'm at my parent's house and they have a Grundig stereo from
好的，这是我爸妈家，他们有个 Grundig 立体声系统
about... what is it? 1995?
好像是......1995年的?
Mother: ummm, yes?
老妈：好像是的吧
About '95, '94. So, let's see if it works with this one...
94年左右生产的，看看这个行不行
Now, I have a sneaky suspicion that we might get a different output from this system.
我总觉得这个能放出些不同的声音
which I'll explain more about, in a second. Let's try
一会我再说，咱先放着看看
SuperBart: 想起当时听广播，中国之声在12:00之后就像这样，停止转播了
Ahhhh, yes, there we go.
好吧，就是这样
Now THIS is what the warning is for. It's nothing outrageous or shocking really is it?
那个警告就是为了这个，虽然这个一点都不吓人:-\
This time, we're just hearing this Grundig unit play the raw binary patterns from the
这回，CD播放器误把数据区当成音频播放了
data track as audio.
It's not going to destroy your system, or send you foaming at the mouth, but I guess
当然，现在这样不会将喇叭给弄坏，或让你觉得很难受
if you had the volume turned up high, it might cause auditory pain, or at worst, blow your speakers.
如果我把声音调高，也许耳朵就该疼了，或是把音响给搞坏:-(
So, how come the Sanyo played nothing, yet this Grundig system emited what can only be
那么，为什么三洋那台啥音都没有，但是
described as a ZX Spectrum tape on steroids?
Grundig却能播放出类似ZX电脑程序磁带的声音呢？
Oh also, thank you to my parents for letting me borrow this stereo we bought in the mid '90s
差点忘了，感谢我父母让我在他们的老音响上面做实验:-)
SuperBart: 我曾经经常“借用”我妈的小米2S电信版刷机，经常搞坏，我现在十分愧疚:-(
The reason for this is due to how these sound systems are designed.
因为这两个东西的设计有所不同
But to explain the design, we first must look at the structure of the data on a CD.
在介绍设计之前，我们先来看看CD上数据的结构吧
The Compact Disc Digital Audio standard was established in the joint Philips and Sony
音乐CD标准是在1981年由飞利浦和索尼共同发布的
注：公认的最早一批CD是索尼在1982年10月1日在日本发行的50张CD
其中编号35DP-4的是Pink Floyd的Wish You Were Here
实际上最早生产出来的CD是在欧洲宝丽多发行的ABBA-The Visitors
不过只是为了宣传，而且三种原型，有两种貌似无法播放
Red Book release way back in 1981 - the red book being essentially just a rule book named
其标准又称“红皮书”，因为那本音乐CD标准书封面就是红色的
so, after it's binding colour, but it's also the start of a rainbow of these books, defining
而这又是规定CD标准的“彩虹书”系列的开端
further standards.
The yellow book would follow in 1984, and its purpose was to define the Compact Disc
“黄皮书”于1984年发布，它规定了CD-ROM格式
注：全名是 只读CD数据光盘
Read Only Memory format.
The same format - of course - used to store data on this Zool 2 CD.
当然，这个规范也用在了 Zool 2 CD上
The significant difference between the two is that the audio CD allows for 2,352 bytes
这两个标准的区别是，音乐CD每个扇区（或称时间帧）
per sector (or timecode frames, if you prefer), plus 98 control bytes which hold the timing
有2352比特的数据，附带98比特的时间数据
information which you see on your Stereo LCD display.
也就是你在播放器LCD屏幕上看到的东西
The CD-ROM structure however, splits that sector up into 12 bytes for synchronisation,
而CD-ROM的数据结构有所不同，有12比特的同步数据
4 bytes for header information, 288 bytes for error correction and 2,048 bytes for the
4比特扇区ID数据，288比特纠错数据，以及2,048比特的数据
actual data itself.
So, if you put a CD with a data track into a fairly recent CD player, it will be able
因此，如果你将有数据区的CD放入近期生产的CD播放机的话
to recognise the data track structure and either throw you an error when you try and
它能够认出数据区的数据结构，然后可能会显示错误
play it, or in the case of my Sanyo, simply silence out the noise of what it perceives
或像我的三洋机那样，侦测到后没有声音放出来
as incorrectly structured data.
If you have an older stereo, which hasn't been programmed to ascertain whether data
如果你家里的CD播放器比较老旧，没有在播放前
is actually formatted as Compact Disc Digital Audio before belting it out, then it will
侦测到CD-ROM的数据结构的话，他就半推半就地播放了
simply attempt to play it as it comes.
Despite the differences in the format, the stereo will just start reading a large, single
因为无法侦测格式上的不同，播放器误认为全盘只有
track of - what it presumes to be sweet, sweet melody - which it will stream directly out
一个音频轨道，姑且认为是个好听的组曲，然后就放了出来
SuperBart: 当我听ELP的Tarkus组曲的时候，看到了七个CD轨道，换轨时那个停顿啊:-(
I mean, the chances of someone even having a CD-ROM to put in their spanking new CD player
当然，在九十年代中叶之前，基本没人将CD-ROM
注：因为CD-ROM九十年代才开始真正地流行
were incredibly low until the mid 90s, so building in these checks just wasn't deemed
塞进全新的CD播放机，所以那时也就没有必要开发这种功能了
that necessary.
But you may point out that the Grundig stereo is actually from the mid 90s, and about the
但这台 Grundig 也是九十年代中叶时候出品的啊
same age as the Sanyo, so how come the difference in playback?
和三洋那台出品年代相同啊，那为何这个能播放呢？
Well, this, as I suspected is down to the quality of the goods.
好吧，我之前的怀疑都是因为这个的质量不好
Both systems are modern enough to weed out data tracks, however, because the Grundig
这两个东西都应该能侦测到数据区，但是
is a cheaper system, it likely utilises components which just don't care.
Grundig 更廉价，看上去就算侦测到了也照放无误
Perhaps older components, or just cheaper components, but regardless, the Grundig has
也许是部件老化或是部件太廉价了，无论如何
no idea as to what a data track is, so it does it's best to play it as CD audio, and
它貌似无法分辨数据区，所以就尽力播放CD了
it really is the CD player attempting to process the binary pits and lands of the CD surface,
它也确实尽力地解读了CD上所包含的内容了
老爹：摘掉面具的配方是长颈鹿的鞋带......长颈鹿不穿鞋的！
as an uncompressed wave format.
并将其转换为声音
The result of this, is noise streaming in at a relatively high baud rate, and if we
结果就是这样的高频声音
slow down the audio, perhaps to a more familiar speed, then it starts to sound just a little
如果我们将音频的速率降到我们可接受的程度
bit more like an 80s home computer
这个声音就很像八十年代的老电脑磁带声了
ahhhhh, yes
o(*￣︶￣*)o
or even a dial up modem from the 90s.
或是九十年代时的拨号上网声音
SuperBart: 我爸妈一个都没接触过这个，再看看David Murray大叔
哎，可想当时我国和外国的差距超级大的，都差不多岁数啊
it's blissful
这挺好的
I could just drift off to this.
我可以一直听着这个睡觉
Maybe we'll play Zool 2 another day.
也许回来我再评测 Zool 2 吧
Now this might have been a bit of a silly video
虽然这个视频有点太简单了
but hopefully I've explained a few noggins of interest.
但兴许大家能从这个视频了解到一些有趣的小知识呢
That's all I can hope for really.
那样就太好了
Anyway, thanks for watching, and hopefully, I'll see you next time!
无论如何，感谢大家收看，我们下期再见:-)
本片由SuperBart翻译
原作者由Nostalgia Nerd发布
发布于2019年1月16日